all right now that you know the basic
Syntax for a web page let's break down
the highest level elements and we're
going to refer to the specification and
we're also going to use uh vs code to
help us so um if you type HTML F if you
HTML ah you type HTML you can see you
can push the arrow keys up and down and
go to HTML 5 and hit enter and it will
actually fill out the beginning of a web
page for you we're going to talk about
what these are
um so the structure of this is
documented in the the specification
which is where is it here it is um and
you know this is where we learn about
what uh the dock type is um writing HTML
documents this is again the spec which
is another video about why and how to
use the spec and here we go start tags
it's we talk about start and dead tags
all that but the doc type is important
you understand this um the doc type is
technically not a part of the HTML it
says that hey get ready here comes a
document doc type HTML is the only valid
reason to do this you will see lots and
lots of pages out there that don't do
this that use the old one in fact if you
want to write a web crawler to hack a
bunch of sites look for all the websites
that don't do this because if they don't
do this their the website's more than 20
years out of date at this point or
actually 15 something like that so make
sure you add a doc type HTML to the
beginning um the next the rest of the
structure of of a document can be
summarized um pretty simply by dividing
the page into two main parts the body
and the
head uh I'm careful not to say header or
heading those all have a very specific
meaning in
HTML um so that stuff is under the HTML
syntax uh par HTML document see no no
NOP NOP no we don't need to do any of
that where is
it um this might be a place where W3 uh
HTML tutorial might be better for you if
you want to go through W3
schools um just I I talked at the other
video about being careful to get to make
you don't depend on this entirely um but
this will give you the basic structure
here and you can go check it out um
there's there's this is one of the many
places uh I talk about where you should
learn it preo Camp's another one but um
you know find your best resource but I
do recommend that you go to the standard
um that you at least know how to go to
the standard to look it up um is this
HTML 5 yes HTML versus XML common
infrastructure um I'm looking for the
web page part Ving resources oh wait
this is
um I'm missing I'm missing ing my link
where is it um the elements of HTML
there we go that's what I wanted the
elements of HTML so again an element is
a key value could be a start and end tag
you know it's got the the tags are the
things with the angle brackets around
them the less than are greater than
signs and then we here here we have the
document so we have the HTML element uh
we can click on that and then learn
about the HTML element uh you don't
necessarily have to know about the Dom
but but before we get too far along um I
do want to talk about the I should have
talked about it in the other video but
now is a good time so what is the Dom
the Dom is the document object model
that governs all of this stuff um h i
did another video on the document web
versus the applications web streaming
web and stuff like that make sure you
watch that uh to understand the
difference but the document web is the
original web and the Paradigm for
knowledge you know transfer is document
as in you know something with a
paragraph a section and all that kind of
thing and it's really important you
understand that because the document
object model um which we will not get
into too deeply we're going to but it
does help you understand this the
structure of of a document in general um
the idea of it having heading and you
know Footers and paragraphs and things
like that um that is the fundamental uh
original original idea behind um behind
HTML and so the document object model
has has has maintained that now the
document object model refers to many
other things
besides um you know just how the the
page is is outlined um it's come to
include things that really don't fall
under the category of documents such as
divs and and and for that
reason um you know the the the term
document in Doc object model starts to
kind of you know lose its value when you
start looking at uh using the Dom for
JavaScript the reason I thought about
this is because this IDL the stand for
interface definition language um this
defines uh stuff that normally you would
see in
JavaScript uh or some other language for
manipulating this document object model
so this is the way the thing would be
implemented underneath uh you know in
inside of the web browser or something
like that um but so I I guess it suffice
to say that you're going to hear about
the Dom a lot about the do document
object model about the idea that um that
everything in in in a particular
document is a has a document object
model so um to give you a sense of this
let me actually put something in this
document here and I'll show you what I
mean um so when you save this here uh
here refresh here okay so now we have
something we can insect element which we
talk about in another video and you can
you can click on Console here and you
see there's our dock type and our head
and our body HTML and uh which we'll
talk about in a bit but what I want to
show you right now is if you go to the
console this is a little bit of a
preview of the JavaScript stuff which
we'll eventually do but not as a part
this particular part of the Boost which
we're focused on documents um so when
you do when you do this you can say
document and you see that the base of
everything in here is a document so this
is where this idea of the Dom comes from
in fact if you do document location you
can print out um you can see up here
there's the URL uh of of the document
and you can see all the the stuff that
comes with the document object model uh
so these are all attri you know these
are all things that are happening behind
the scenes um with regard to uh just
this you know humble little document
page right here um and again I'm
avoiding the temptation to drill down
into um into all of this right now we
just care about the elements on the page
head and body so let's go back and talk
about that so we see uh again doc type
HTML is not an element this is um an
HTML uh element if anything that's what
put the initial exclamation point and
then we have HTML element with this
attribute Lang defining the language uh
that's not mandated but you know this
particular template suggests we do that
we're going to talk about the utf8 uh
character sets separately with the meta
tag but but but here is the head which
has uh non-printed stuff in it and then
we have the body um which has the stuff
that appears on the page um the only
place you see stuff in the head is
usually in the title which I talk about
separately um and you see how it say
document there so we could change that
to be whatever we wanted to um let's go
back and just finish reading the
specification uh summaries for these
other element types so we have we have
HTML we have head let's read about that
so what is the head head the first
element HTML it has to be the first by
the way um do I frame don't care about
that head element start tag can be
emitted if the element is empty uh or if
it's firsted inside the so you can
actually leave the head element off and
as you saw that's exactly what we did uh
we we could do that and it would be
added we didn't in this one but but we
could leave it off and be added um let's
see it's a global attribute uh it
contains attributes that apply to
everything
uh so here we go so here is the head and
we can have the title in there um so
let's let's keep going let's go back to
the uh the title okay so this is um so
the base in the title appear in the head
same with link I don't know if we want
talk about and meta we're going to talk
about these when we talk about the head
element we're going to do a whole thing
just on the head element so let's jump
forward to the body element um so the
the body element um
contains uh all the body and that that
includes um the stuff that uh well let
me show you so you're going to see me
doing this a lot by the way we're going
to be going out to the web pages so I
can find it here we go um one oh wait I
was right there all right here we go so
uh inspect element and we're going to go
to here you can type document min.
body body okay see that how it selected
it and now you can see so I'm using the
Dom I'm using JavaScript I'm using the
Dom from JavaScript to look it up and
you can see now I can see the attributes
from it uh we can see that there was a
script element injected into the body uh
this was injected by um by my by my dark
reader if I turn my dark reader off we
all go blind but that stuff will go away
um but as you can see you can actually
drill down into the docum object models
the document. body um and you can see uh
the different the different elements
that are in here so uh and there's code
injected by live server that is a
comment and so that gets us that gets us
down to where we want to be uh which
really for right now is what what are
the main you know parts of a of a of web
page we have the doc type you know uh
tag at the very top and then we have a
head right and then we have a body right
and we're going to talk about these
these all the other pieces come inside
of either a head or a body we're going
to talk about them separately okay so
that's it so by now you should know that
every web page is is broken down into
two major parts a head and a body and
every modern web page begins with dotop
HTML